Barbara Cooney Papers
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Barbara Cooney Papers
1953-1999
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center
Cooney, Barbara.
58 linear feet
Barbara Cooney (1917-2000) was a freelance author and illustrator of over one hundred children's books.
MSS19970102
Biography
Barbara Cooney was born 6 August 1917, in Brooklyn, NY, the daughter of Russell Schenck (a stockbroker) and Mae Evelyn (an artist; maiden name, Bossert) Cooney. She was educated at Smith College (B.A., 1938) and attended the Art Students League (1940). During World War II she served in the Women's Army Corps (1942-1943), achieving the rank of second lieutenant.
A freelance author and illustrator (1938-2000), Cooney's works are also held in the Kerlan Collection at the University of Minnesota, the de Grummond Collection at the University of Southern Mississippi, and in museums at Rutgers University, Bowdoin College, and in the public libraries of Gary, Indiana, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
She is the recipient of many awards for her work:
New York Herald Tribune's Children's Spring Book Festival Honor Book. Green Wagons, 1943; Too Many Pets, 1952.
American Library Association Notable Book citation. American Folk Songs for Children in Home, School and Nursery School, 1948; Chanticleer and the Fox, 1958; Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose, 1974.
Caldecott Medal from the American Library Association. Chanticleer and the Fox, 1959; Ox-Cart Man, 1980.
Chandler Book Talk Award of Merit, 1964.
Child Study Association of America Children's Books of the Year. Christmas Folk and The Owl and the Pussy-Cat, 1969; Hermes, Lord of Robbers and Book of Princesses, 1971; Down to the Beach, 1973; Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose, 1974; Lexington and Concord, 1775, 1975; The Story of Holly and Ivy, Christmas in the Barn, The Little Fir Tree and Emma, 1986.
School Library Journal's Best Books List Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose, 1974.
New York Times Outstanding Books of the Year Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose, 1974; When the Sky Is Like Lace, 1975; Ox-Cart Man, 1979.
Silver Medallion from the University of Southern Mississippi 1975, for outstanding contributions to the field of children's books.
Medal from Smith College 1976, for her body of work.
New York Times Best Illustrated Books of the Year Ox-Cart Man, 1979.
Notable Children's Trade Book in the Field of Social Studies, National Council for the Social Studies and Children's Book Council Tortillitas para Mama and Other Nursery Rhymes, 1982; The Story of Holly and Ivy, 1986.
American Book Award for Hardcover Picture Book from the Association of American Publishers Miss Rumphius, 1983.
New York Times Best Book of the Year Miss Rumphius, 1983.
Notable Children's Book, Association for Library Services to Children, American Library Association Spirit Child, 1984.Honor list Island Boy, 1989
Ph.D., Fitchburg State College, 1988.
Keene State College Children's Literature Festival Award, 1989.
McCord Children's Literature Citation, 1990.
Lupine Award for Hattie and the Wild Waves, 1990.
Kerlan Award, 1992, for body of work.
Honorary doctorates from the University of Maine at Machais (1994), Westbrook College (1995), and Bowdoin College (1996).
Proclaimed an official state treasure of Maine, 1996.
Cooney died after a long illness on 10 March 2000.
Cooney Bibliography
Author and Illustrator:
The King of Wreck Island, Farrar & Rinehart, 1941.
The Kellyhorns, Farrar & Rinehart, 1942.
Captain Pottle's House, Farrar, 1943.
(Adapter) Geoffrey Chaucer. Chanticleer and the Fox, Crowell, 1958.
The Little Juggler: Adapted from an Old French Legend, Hastings House, 1961, 1982.
(Adapter). The Courtship, Merry Marriage, and Feast of Cock Robin and Jenny Wren: To Which Is Added the Doleful Death of Cock Robin, Scribner, 1965.
(Adapter) Jacob Grimm and Wilhelm Grimm. Snow White and Rose Red, Delacorte, 1966.
Christmas, Crowell, 1967
revised edition published as The Story of Christmas, illustrated by Loretta Krupinski HarperCollins, 1995.
(Editor) A Little Prayer, Hastings House, 1967.
A Garland of Games and Other Diversions: An Alphabet Book, Holt, 1969.
Miss Rumphius, Viking, 1982.
(Reteller) J. Grimm. Little Brother and Little Sister, Doubleday, 1982.
Island Boy, Viking, 1988.
Hattie and the Wild Waves, Viking, 1990.
Eleanor, Viking, 1996.
Illustrator:
Bertil Malmberg. Ake and His World, Farrar & Rinehart, 1940.
Frances M. Frost. Uncle Snowball, Farrar & Rinehart, 1940.
Oskar Seidlin and Senta Rypins. Green Wagons, Houghton, 1943.
Anne Molloy. Shooting Star Farm, Houghton, 1946.
Phyllis Crawford. The Blot: Little City Cat, Holt, 1946.
Nancy Hartwell. Shoestring Theater, Holt, 1947.
L. L. Bein. Just Plain Maggie, Harcourt, 1948.
Lee Kingman. The Rocky Summer, Houghton, 1948.
Ruth Crawford Seeger. American Folk Songs for Children in Home, School and Nursery School: A Book for Children, Parents and Teachers, Doubleday, 1948
Linnet, 1993
Child Study Association of America. Read Me Another Story, Crowell, 1949.
Rutherford George Montgomery. Kildee House, Doubleday, 1949
Walker, 1994.
Lee Kingman. The Best Christmas, Doubleday, 1949
reprinted Peter Smith, 1985
Phyllis Krasilovsky. The Man Who Didn't Wash His Dishes, Doubleday, 1950.
Ruth Crawford Seeger. Animal Folk Songs for Children: Traditional American Songs, Doubleday, 1950.
Nellie M. Leonard. Graymouse Family, Crowell, 1950.
Child Study Association of America. Read Me More Stories, Crowell, 1951.
Rutherford George Montgomery. Hill Ranch, Doubleday, 1951.
Elisabeth C. Lansing. The Pony That Ran Away, Crowell, 1951.
Lee Kingman. Quarry Adventure,, Doubleday, 1951
published in England as Lauri's Surprising Summer Constable, 1957
Elisabeth C. Lansing. The Pony That Kept a Secret, Crowell, 1952.
Mary M. Aldrich. Too Many Pets, Macmillan, 1952.
Margaret Wise Brown. Where Have You Been?, Crowell, 1952
reprinted, Scholastic Book Services, 1966
Barbara Reynolds. Pepper, Scribner, 1952.
Miriam E. Mason. Yours with Love, Kate, Houghton, 1952.
Margaret Wise Brown. Christmas in the Barn, Crowell, 1952.
Catherine Marshall. Let's Keep Christmas, Whittlesey House, 1953.
Ruth Crawford Seeger. American Folk Songs for Christmas, Doubleday, 1953.
Nellie M. Leonard. Grandfather Whiskers, M. D.: A Graymouse Story, Crowell, 1953.
Lee Kingman. Peter's Long Walk, Doubleday, 1953.
Elisabeth C. Lansing. A Pony Worth His Salt, Crowell, 1953.
Jane Quigg. Fun for Freddie, Oxford University Press, 1953.
Margaret Sidney. The Five Little Peppers, Doubleday, 1954.
Margaret Wise Brown. The Little Fir Tree, Crowell, 1954
reissued, 1985
Margaret G. Otto. Pumpkin, Ginger, and Spice, Holt, 1954.
Helen Kay (pseudonym of Helen C. Goldfrank). Snow Birthday, Farrar, Straus, 1955.
Louisa May Alcott. Little Women; or, Meg, Jo, Beth, and Amy, Crowell, 1955.
Louise A. Kent. The Brookline Trunk, Houghton, 1955.
Catherine S. McEwen. Away We Go! One-Hundred Poems for the Very Young, Crowell, 1956.
Catherine Marshall. Friends with God: Stories and Prayers of the Marshall Family, Whittlesey House, 1956.
H. Kay. City Springtime, Hastings House, 1957.
Neil Anderson (pseudonym of Jerrold Beim). Freckle Face, Crowell, 1957.
Henrietta Buckmaster. Lucy and Loki, Scribner, 1958.
Harry Behn. Timmy's Search, Seabury, 1958.
Margaret G. Otto. Little Brown Horse, Knopf, 1959.
Elizabeth George Speare. Seasonal Verses Gathered by Elizabeth George Speare from the Connecticut Almanack for the Year of the Christian Era, 1773, American Library Association, 1959.
(French adaptation of The Owl and the Pussycat by Edward Lear) translated by Francis Steegmuller. Le Hibou et la Poussiquette, Little, Brown, 1961.
Walter de la Mare. Peacock Pie: A Book of Rhymes, Knopf, 1961.
Noah Webster. The American Speller: An Adaptation of Noah Webster's Blue-Backed Speller, Crowell, 1961.
Margaret G. Otto. Three Little Dachshunds, Holt, 1963.
Sarah Orne Jewett. A White Heron: A Story of Maine, Crowell, 1963.
Virginia Haviland. Favorite Fairy Tales Told in Spain, Little, Brown, 1963.
(French adaptation of Wynken, Blynken, and Nod by Eugene Field), translated by F. Steegmuller and Norbert Guterman. Papillot, Clignot, et Dodo, Farrar, Straus, 1964.
Hugh Latham, translator. Mother Goose in French, Crowell, 1964.
Anne Molloy. Shaun and the Boat: An Irish Story, Hastings House, 1965.
Jane Goodsell. Katie's Magic Glasses, Houghton, 1965.
Samuel Morse. All in a Suitcase, Little, Brown, 1966.
Aldous Huxley. Crowns of Pearblossom, Random House, 1967.
Alastair Reid and Anthony Kerrigan. Mother Goose in Spanish, Crowell, 1968.
Edward Lear. The Owl and the Pussy-Cat, Little, Brown, 1969.
Natalia M. Belting. Christmas Folk, Holt, 1969.
Eugene Field. Wynken, Blynken and Nod, Hastings House, 1970.
William Wise. The Lazy Young Duke of Dundee, Rand McNally, 1970.
Homer. Dionysus and the Pirates: Homeric Hymn Number 7, translated and adapted by Penelope Proddow. Doubleday, 1970.
Felix Salten (pseudonym of Siegmund Salzman. Bambi: A Life in the Woods, Simon & Schuster, 1970.
Book of Princesses, Scholastic Book Services, 1971.
Homer. Hermes, Lord of Robbers: Homeric Hymn Number Four, translated and adapted by Penelope Proddow Doubleday, 1971.
Homer. Demeter and Persephone: Homeric Hymn Number Two, translated and adapted by Penelope Proddow Doubleday, 1972.
John Becker. Seven Little Rabbits, Walker, 1972
1994
May Garelick. Down to the Beach, Four Winds, 1973.
Robyn Supraner. Would You Rather Be a Tiger?, Houghton, 1973.
Dorothy Joan Harris. The House Mouse, Warner, 1973.
Edna Mitchell Preston. Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose, Viking, 1974.
Zora L. Olsen. Herman the Great, Scholastic Book Services, 1974.
Elinor L. Horwitz. When the Sky Is Like Lace, Lippincott, 1975.
Jean Poindexter Colby. Lexington and Concord, 1775: What Really Happened, Hastings House, 1975.
Edna Mitchell Preston. The Sad Story of the Little Bluebird and the Hungry Cat, Four Winds, 1975.
Marjorie Weinman Sharmat. Burton and Dudley, Holiday House, 1975.
M. Jean Craig. The Donkey Prince, Doubleday, 1977.
Aileen Fisher. Plant Magic, Bowmar, 1977.
Ellin Greene, compiler. Midsummer Magic: A Garland of Stories, Charms, and Recipes, Lothrop, 1977.
Donald Hall. Ox-Cart Man, Viking, 1979.
Delmore Schwartz. I Am Cherry Alive, the Little Girl Sang, Harper, 1979.
Norma Farber. How the Hibernators Came to Bethlehem, Walker, 1980.
Wendy Ann Kesselman. Emma, Doubleday, 1980.
Margot C. Griego and others, selectors and translators. Tortillitas para Mama and Other Nursery Rhymes: Spanish and English, Holt, 1982.
John Bierhorst, translator. Spirit Child: A Story of the Nativity, Morrow, 1984.
Rumer Godden. The Story of Holly and Ivy, Viking, 1985.
Sergei Prokofiev. Peter and the Wolf: A Mechanical Book, Viking, 1985.
Toni de Gerez, reteller. Louhi, Witch of North Farm, Viking, 1986.
Gloria Houston. The Year of the Perfect Christmas Tree: An Appalachian Tale, Dial, 1988.
Alice McLerran. Roxaboxen, Lothrop, 1991.
Michael Bedard. Emily, Doubleday, 1992.
Jane Yolen. Letting Swift River Go, Little, Brown, 1992.
Ruth Sawyer. The Remarkable Christmas of the Cobbler's Sons, Viking, 1994.
Opal Whiteley. Only Opal: The Diary of a Young Girl, selected and adapted by Jane Boulton, Philomel, 1994.
Mary Lyn Ray. Basket Moon, Little, Brown, 1998.
Other:
Twenty-Five Years A-Graying: The Portrait of a College Graduate, a Pictorial Study of the Class of 1938 at Smith College, Northampton, Massachusetts, Based on Statistics Gathered in 1963 for the Occasion of Its 25th Reunion, Little, Brown, 1963.
Media Adaptations:
Chanticleer and the Fox, was adapted as a sound filmstrip by Weston Woods, 1959.
Wynken, Blynken and Nod, was adapted as a sound filmstrip by Weston Woods, 1967.
Owl and the Pussycat was adapted as a sound filmstrip, 1967.
The Man Who Didn't Wash His Dishes was adapted as a sound filmstrip by Weston Woods, 1973.
Squawk to the Moon, Little Goose was adapted as a sound filmstrip by Viking, 1975.
Miss Rumphius was adapted as a filmstrip with cassette by Live Oak Media, 1984.
Ox-Cart Man was adapted as a filmstrip with cassette by Random House and as a videocassette by
and as a videocassette by Live Oak Media.
How the Hibernators Came to Bethlehem was adapted as a filmstrip with cassette by Random House.
American Folk Songs for Children was adapted as a cassette.
Scope and Content
The collection contains preliminary and finished artwork for 23 titles. Materials include dummies, preliminary artwork, sketches, book jackets, finished art, galleys and proofs.
Related Material
Archives and Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature artwork. See especially Loretta Krupinski Papers. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Barbara Cooney interview 1997-0102.vr1
Miss Rumphus 1997-0102.cd1
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by book publication date.
Bibliography
Children's Literature Review, Volume 23, Detroit: Gale, 1991.
Colby, Jean Poindexter. Writing, Illustrating, and Editing Children's Books. New York: Hastings House, 1967.
Field, Elinor W. Horn Book Reflections. Boston:, Horn Book, 1969.
Fuller, Muriel, editor. More Junior Authors. Bronx, NY:, H. W. Wilson, 1963, pp. 53-54.
Georgiou, Constantine. Children and Their Literature, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1969.
Hopkins, Lee Bennett. Books Are by People. New York: Citation Press, 1969 ,pp. 42-43.
Hurlimann, Bettina. Picture-Book World. World Publishing, 1969.
Klemin, Diana. The Art of Art for Children's Books. New York: C. N. Potter, 1966.
Roginski, Jim, compiler. Newbery and Caldecott Medalists and Honor Book Winners. Littleton, CO: Libraries Unlimited, 1982.
Twentieth Century Children's Writers. Fourth edition. Detroit: St. James Press, 1995.
Booklist, November 1, 1990, p. 528; February 1, 1994, pp. 980, 984; March 15, 1995, p. 348.
Bulletin of the Center for Children's Books, December, 1990, pp. 81-82; November, 1996, pp. 93-94.
Chicago Tribune--Books, November 2, 1958, p. 11.
Children's Literature Association Quarterly, winter, 1984-85, pp. 152-53.
Horn Book Magazine, August, 1959, pp. 310-14; October, 1960, pp. 386-87; February, 1980, pp. 44-45; August, 1980, pp. 378-82, 383-87; November, 1988, pp. 769-70; September, 1992, p. 581; January-February, 1994, pp. 110-11; May, 1994; September-October, 1996, pp. 610-11.
Instructor, March, 1985, pp. 94-96.
Junior Bookshelf, December, 1980, pp. 283-84; December, 1989, p. 262.
Kirkus Reviews, October 1, 1988, p. 1467; October 15, 1995, p. 1488.
Los Angeles Times Book Review, November 20, 1988, p. 8.
New York Times Book Review, November 2, 1958, p. 2; December 4, 1968, p. 40; November 11, 1979, p. 51; April 25, 1982, p. 42; November 14, 1982, p. 43; December 4, 1988, p. 40; January 6, 1991, p. 26; December 8, 1996, p. 78.
Publishers Weekly, March 23, 1959; July 9, 1982, p. 49; July 29, 1988, p. 138; June 29, 1990, p. 68; March, 1991, pp. 194-95; April 12, 1991, p. 57; September 18, 1995, p. 103; October 14, 1996, pp. 31-32.
School Library Journal, October, 1988, pp. 116-17; October, 1995, p. 36; September, 1996, pp. 195-96.
Washington Post Book World, May 9, 1982, p. 16; November 6, 1988, p. 14.
Portland Press Herald, March 14, 2000, p.1A.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Cooney, Barbara, 1917-
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives and Special Collections by the estate of Barbara Cooney in 2001.
Detailed Description/Box and Folder Listing
- Books,1953-1999
  - Grandfather Whiskers, M.D., A Graymouse Story. Nellie M. Leonard. Thomas Y. Crowell, 1953
    - Jacket, 4 photostats, pp. VI, pp. 6, 7, 14, 19, 29, 37, 41, 42, 53, 62, 69, 77, 82, 84, 95, 105, 106, 113, 127, 135, 140, 142, 151, 158, 160, 164, 179, 181, 187, 189, 197, 199, 209, 1 sketch (Box MC 11)
  - Seasonal Verses Gathered by Elizabeth George Speare from the Connecticut Almanack for the Year of the Christian Era, 17. Elizabeth George Speare. American Library Association (Chicago), 1959.
    - Book, sketches, paste-up, loose printed illustrations (Box 8)
  - The American Speller, adapted from Noah Webster's " Blue-Backed Speller." Thomas Crowell, 1960.
    - pp. 2, 4, 6, 8, 9, 11, 12, 16, 17, 19-26, 28, 29-31, 33-41, 43-56, 58-61, 63-69 (Box MC 11)
  - Favorite Fairy Tale Told in Spain. Virginia Haviland. Little, 1963.
    - pp. 16, 26, 33, 53, 5 sketches, 2 proofs (Box MC 11)
  - A White Heron. Sara Orne Jewett. Thomas Y. Crowell, 1963.
    - (by Book) jacket, title page, pp. 1-3, 5-6, 10-13, 16-17, 19, 22-25, 27, 29-32, 35, 4 sketches (Box MC 11)
  - Mother Goose in French. Translated by Hough Latham. Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1964.
    - pp. 6-13, 16-23, 25-30, 33-37, 42-43 (Box MC 11)
  - Papillot, Clignot Et Dodo. Eugene Field, translated by Francis Steegmuller and Norbert Guterman. Farrar Straus, 1964.
    - jacket, endpaper, title page, opening of text, pp. 1-6, 10-13 (Box MC11)
  - Snow-White and Rose-Red. Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm, adapted by Barbara Cooney. Constable Ltd., 1964.
    - jacket, frontis, pp. 5, 6-20, 25, 26-27, 29-31, 33-35, 37-39, 41-46, 4 sketches (Box MC 11)
  - A Littel Prayer. Barbara Cooney. Hastings, 1967.
    - jacket, pp. 3, 6-11, 13-24, 26, 30 (Box MC 11)
  - Mother Goose In Spanish. Alsatair Reid and Anthony Kerrigan. Thomas Y. Crowell, 1968.
    - pp. 22-23, 30-31 (Box MC 11)
  - Christmas Folk. Natalia Belting. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1969.
    - pp. 2-3, 8-9, 11-13, 16-19, 20-21, 26-29, 32-33, 35-37, 4 sketches (Box MC 11)
  - Hermes, Lord of Robbers. Homer, translated by Penelope Proddow. Doubleday, 1971.
    - pp. 4-5, 8, 10-11, 36-37 (Box MC 11)
  - Demeter and Persephone. Homer, translated by Penelope Proddow. Doubleday, 1972.
    - pp. 15, 20-21, 22-23, 27 (Box MC11)
  - Donkey Prince. M. Jean Craig. Doubleday, 1977.
    - Dummy, Jacket, test illustrations, pp. 1-2, 6-7, 8-14, 17, 19, 23, 25-26, 28-29, 31, 33, 35, 37, 39, 41 (Box MC 11)
  - "I am Cherry Alive" The Little Girl Sang. Delmore Schwartz. Harper and Row, 1978.
    - pp. 2, 3, 7, 13, 14, 19, 26-29, 10 unused and 1 unknown illustration (Box MC 11)
  - Tortillitas Para Mama. Translated by Margot C. Griego, Betsy L. Bucks, Sharon S. Gilbert, and Laurel H. Kimball. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1981.
    - cover, pp. 6, 9, 11, 12-15, 18-21, 23, 25-27 (Box MC 11)
  - Spirit Child: a story of the Nativity. Bernardino de Sahagun, translated from the Aztec by John Bierhorst. Morrow, 1984.
    - Jacket, pp. 3, 7-8, 10/11-14/15, 17 and alternate, 18/19-20/21, 23, 24/25-28/29, 31-32 (Box MC 11)
  - Louhi, Witch Of North Farm. Toni de Gerez. Viking, 1986.
    - Jacket, pp. 1-3, 6-13, 16-25, 28-29, dummy, overlays (Box MC 11)
  - The Year of the Perfect Christmas Tree. Gloria Houston. Dial, 1988.
    - Dummy, 2 jacket sketches, pp. 1, 5, 3-7, 8, 9, 13, 14, 16, 17-23, 27-32 (Box MC 11)
  - Roxaboxen. Alice McLerran. Lothrop, Lee and Shepard, 1991.
    - Proofs, dummy, pp. 3, 5, 6-7, 9, 10, 13, 15, 17, 18, 21, 22-23, 24-25, 26, 27, 28, 30-31 (Box 2)
  - Letting Swift River Go. Jane Yolen. Little, Brown, 1992.
    - dummy, sketches, jacket, title page, pp. 5-13, 14-16, 18-19, 2-22, 24-27, 30-32 (Box MC 11)
  - Emily. Michael Bedard. Doubleday, 1992.
    - Dummy, exhibit labels, book sleeve, sketches, roll, jacket, pp. 1, 3, 5-11, 14, 15, 16 or 17, 18, 19, 23, 24, 27-29, 31-35 (Box 5-7)
  - The Remarkable Christmas of the Cobbler's Sons. Ruth Sawyer. Viking, 1994.
    - p. 15 framed jacket/cover (Box 3)
    - pp. 1-11, 13, 15-19, 21, 23, 25-26, 28-32 (Box 4)
  - Basket Moon. Mary Lyn Ray. Little, Brown, 1998.
    - Dummy, pp. 6-32 (Box 1)